PROFESSOR: Everything in minimax and
expectimax search has made reference
to the idea that there are utilities
that you can go around, either
maximizing or taking averages of.
What are these numbers?
Where do they come from?
And how do we know they even exist?
If we had numbers that represented
our preferences, why are we
even averaging them?
So before we compute what these
utilities are, why did we ever talk
about anything other than minimax I
mean, after all, we understand minimax
pretty well, and it gives us some
pretty good worst case bounds.
Why don't we always run around
doing minimax search?
The answer is vampire bunnies.
Right?
There are things that your model might
imagine but have such small
probability.
But they're really bad.
And maybe you don't worry so much about
vampire bunnies, but you imagine
things like well, should I go to eat
Thai food or should I go to eat
Italian food?
Well, if I go to eat Thai food, it
might be a little too spicy.
I might get hit by a meteor.
STUDENTS: [LAUGHTER].
PROFESSOR: And then you think about in
the Italian food, well, let's see, it
might be very greasy.
Or I might get hit by a meteor.
And you go around and all of your
computations are dominated by these
events which are very bad
and very unlikely.
Worst case reasoning only works to the
extent that your model is sufficiently
simple, that the really bad, really
rare stuff isn't even considered.
If you want to be robust to the fact
that bad things can happen but usually
don't, you need average
case reasoning.
You really have no choice.
And what that leads us to is the
principle of maximum expected utility.
This principle states that a rational
agent should choose the action that
maximizes its expected utility
given its knowledge.
We've already seen a lot
of this definition.
We already know what it means to take
the best choice, to maximize.
We've seen a lot of that kind
of [? tree-search. ?]
We now know what expectations
are and what expectimax is.
And that really tells you about
expected utilities.
And for the rest of the course, we're
going to spend a lot of energy
unpacking this idea of what is the
expectation, given our knowledge?
And that's going to lead us to
probabilistic inference.
So that's the principle of
maximum expected utility.
But where do these utilities
come from?
How do we know there are utilities that
represent our preferences at all?
How do we know that averaging
even makes sense?
Right?
Maybe you don't think that averaging
these numbers actually still preserves
your preferences.
What if our behavior is
so complex and subtle?
We're humans, right?
Our behavior is so complex and subtle,
we cannot possibly be reduced to a
real valued function.
So what are these utilities?
Utilities are functions from outcomes,
which are states of the world, to real
numbers that encode an
agent's preferences.
Where do these come from?
Well, in a game, it's easy.
It's part of the definition.
Plus one if you win, minus
one if you lose.
Your score, whatever it is.
The utilities have to summarize
the agent's goals.
And there's a theorem that says if
your preferences are basically
reasonable, they can be summarized
by a utility function.
In general, the approach we take with
utilities is to think of the utilities
as the input--
we hard-wire utilities--
and the behavior, the action
selection, as the output.
The behaviors emerge through
computation.
And why do we want this?
Why do we want the goals to be the input
and the optimal behavior to be
the output of the computation?
Why don't we just let agents
pick their own utilities?
What would happen if we let a vacuum
cleaner agent pick its own utility?
And it wanted to then maximize
that utility?
It sits, and it thinks and it thinks
ah, I would like to do nothing.
Right?
And it's so easy to do nothing.
And now it's happy because
it picked its utility.
And it's so happy with its utility.
But it's not what we wanted.
What we say is no, your utility
is picking up dirt.
And now the vacuum cleaner does whatever
it does to maximize that.
We don't want to dictate the behavior,
because we don't want to get into like
drawing the particular pattern it
should trace out on the floor.
The search procedure should
do all that for us.
So we don't want to prescribe
the behavior.
It's very hard to write down behavior,
because behavior is complicated and
context-dependent.
So that's the idea.
Utilities go in.
Behavior comes out.
Now we got to be careful about this,
because if you just tell the vacuum
cleaner your goal is to pick up dirt,
maybe it gets this idea that the best
way to pick up dirt is to pick up dirt,
dump the dirt, pick it up again,
and dump it again.
And so you need to make sure when you
encode these things, you actually mean
what you say.
But you know, that's your problem.
Right?
The vacuum cleaner's just doing
what you told it to do.
All right.
So, utilities.
Let's imagine we have an
ice cream eating robot.
And it looks at these various outcomes
and it says well, you know an ice
cream cone is good.
It's better if it has a scoop in it.
And two scoops is great.
So over these outcomes--
zero, one, or two scoops--
maybe we agree that a reasonable ice
cream cone robot might order
them in this way.
That one is better than zero,
and two is better than one.
However, we're actually going to ask
the robot, in reality, to make
decisions not just amongst number of
scoops, which is easy, but amongst
uncertain outcomes.
So, for example, you imagine
the robot has a choice.
It's getting ice cream.
And it can order a single scoop or
it could order a double scoop.
And if it orders a single scoop, well,
it ends up with a single scoop of ice
cream, which we decided was
kind of in the middle.
What happens if it orders
a double scoop?
Well, the problem with ordering a double
scoop is that's a lot of ice
cream piled high.
Right?
Something bad could happen.
You know, oops, your ice cream is on
the floor, and you have no scoops.
But most of the time, everything's
fine, and you get to
enjoy your yummy scoops.
The agent is going to have to have a
preference between these two outcomes.
Does it prefer the guaranteed single
scoop or does it prefer this uncertain
mix of zero or two?
Well, it's actually OK.
Different utilities are going to make
different choices here, but the point
is the agent's preferences need to
encode whether or not it would choose
single or double in this case.
And the specific numbers we assign are
going to make that determination when
we run an expectimax search.
So what are these preferences?
Well, an agent has to have preferences
among various things.
We know, for example, zero, one,
and two ice cream scoops--
it has to have preferences
amongst what are called
prizes, specific outcomes.
They're called prizes.
They don't have to be wrapped up as
a present or anything like that.
That's just the technical term.
A prize is a specific outcome.
So you have A and B which might
be various numbers of scoops.
We have to have preference among the
prizes, but we also have to be able to
order our preferences amongst lotteries,
which are situations where
you're not sure which prize
you're going to get.
And that's shown here.
So you have prizes, which are atomic
outcomes, and you have lotteries,
which are mixtures with
a certain probability.
And if you look at that, you think
that's exactly what a chance note is.
It creates a little lottery.
And an expectimax tree is really
just a bigger cursive lottery.
So these lotteries and these prizes--
we have to have preferences,
meaning, an agent has to
prefer one or the other.
And the question is just are there
utilities that reflect those
preferences?
So when I say lottery, there
are real lotteries.
There are real lotteries where
you pay your money.
You get your ticket.
You scratch it off.
And you hope it's the right number.
Right?
When we say lottery here, we do
not mean the actual act of
gambling in a lottery.
That's fine.
But that introduces a
lot of complexity.
For example, when you actually play
the lottery, sometimes you win and
sometimes you lose.
But win or lose, you played.
Right?
And that's important, because part of
the reason why people play lotteries
is they like to play lotteries.
When we say lottery here, and we say 50%
chance of A and 50% chance of B,
we do not mean "and the fun of playing."
We simply mean you are not
sure which one's going to happen.
For example, rolling the dice
in a sense is a lottery.